<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-10-09T13:43:05+02:00</updated><id>/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">eugene kudashev finally has a blog???</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">how to find internet friends</title><link href="/blog/how-to-find-internet-friends" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to find internet friends" /><published>2022-09-22T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-22T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/how%20to%20find%20internet%20friends</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/how-to-find-internet-friends"><![CDATA[<style>
hr {
  margin: 2em;
}
</style>

<h2 id="i-met-some-incredible-people-on-twitter-by-accident-what-can-i-do-to-have-more-of-those-accidents">i met some incredible people on twitter by accident. what can i do to have more of those accidents?</h2>

<p>three days ago, i saw a tweet on my timeline (from someone i didn’t follow) that read (i’m paraphrasing) “i want to go back to blogging like it’s 2007” (self-hosted blog, just sharing thoughts and work and ideas, less performative) – a very relatable sentiment. this is something i’ve been thinking about in the past weeks (good job, algorithm), so i left a reply, asking for advice in terms of suitable tools to make it happen. a couple of people replied, and one reached out in DMs. we spoke a bit and it seemed like we had a lot of similar ideas, so we agreed to do a phone call. the next morning, we spoke for an hour, exchanging thoughts and ideas. this felt good.</p>

<p>this could be the beginning of an incredibly classy homosexual erotica. for better or for worse, it isn’t.</p>

<hr />

<p>the reason i’m bringing up this story is that the whole experience felt very reminiscent of the early 2000s internet, when you would just accidentally strike up a conversation with a stranger, and it would be a good thing. somehow, in the past years i can barely remember anything like that happening.</p>

<p>it’s hard to say whether it’s me (rarely replying to strangers’ tweets), or the environments (the algorithms kind of forcing everyone into their bubbles), or both, one influencing the other, both ways (you ask a genuine question and get a mean response, which makes you hesitant to approach strangers, etc.) – but either way, i clearly remember that i used to meet people online, and now i don’t.</p>

<p>it’s incredibly difficult to answer “why”, and also, it doesn’t really matter. what matters is: how do i change that?</p>

<h1 id="what-can-i-do-to-meet-people-who-share-my-interests-values-ideas">what can i do to meet people who share my interests, values, ideas?</h1>

<p>i am tempted to call this “networking that doesn’t feel like networking”. a conversation, a dialogue, which is equally interesting to both parties – unlike two sales pitches, two people mutually disengaged, talking “past each other”. a conversation that is fueled by substance, by <em>what’s being said</em>, not by pursuit of personal gain.</p>

<hr />

<p>the essential requirement for two strangers to start talking is some shared context.</p>

<hr />

<p>LinkedIn is where people speak about their work like they are on a job interview. on Twitter, people speak about their work because they care about their work.</p>

<hr />

<p>this morning i started thinking about some kind of “Discover” feature on top on twitter which would be helpful to me. how could it possibly work?</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>one very obvious direction is to explore my social graph. i’m fairly certain that of some people who i follow, or who follow me, there are people with whom i might have something in common – but we’re unaware of one another’s existence. i assumer that the chances of <em>like-mindedness</em> are much higher within my micro-bubble than within a completely random sample of 1000 people on twitter.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>but bubbles are dangerous precisely because they are bubbles: they are not really inclusive by definition. they greatly limit your discovery opportunities by excluding everyone who is not already in some way connected to you.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>so another direction would be some extremely elegant way to find potential friends based on identifying similarities between you and other people. how can that be done?</p>

    <ul>
      <li>for example, you read an article and liked it so much that you tweeted a link to it. somebody else did the exact same thing. just this one piece of information can suggest that you might have something in common. perhaps that article can become this “shared context” over which you can strike up a conversation?</li>
      <li>of course, this is largely an oversimplification. after all, my tweet might read “oh my god i love this so much”, whereas a stranger’s tweet might read “oh my god i fucking hate this” – so the matchmaking algorithm would need to take this “emotional context” into account as well.</li>
      <li>now, let’s take this a bit further. let’s take not one tweet, but, say, one full month of tweets. this gives us much more information about a person, so we can start building their “profile”. (BIG ETHICAL DANGERS HERE! – <em>editor’s note</em>) we can start identifying recurring themes, their areas of interest, their sense of humour, and we can do better educated guesses on the potential “<strong>contexts of interest</strong>”.</li>
      <li>and so, now let’s imagine everyone has their “profile”, and they can choose to hit a button that, rougly, would read “i want to see someone new [who is, in some way, kinda like me]”</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p><strong>AN INTERMISSION.</strong> Oct 9. i’m reading what i wrote above (about three weks ago) and i’m about to make a counter point. so, i’m making an argument that “it’s bad/not enough to be inside your bubble.” i find this argument hilarious. that’s how like everybody lived for most of human histories: in their villages, in their small communities. their lives revolved around maybe 20-30 other people. that was their bubble and they perfectly managed. so– thanks to the internet, did we finally accepted “people = commodity”? this is sad, very sad. this line of thinking – “there’s ALWAYS someone new” – is dangerous, as it means you don’t value your existing connections enough. so… this is not a critique of what’s above; just an observation.</p>

<p>it’s just probably important to recognize that there’s a limit of people you can keep in your life. reasonably. at SOME proximity. and that you can’t realistically find space for more people.</p>

<p>note: the above paragraph prompted me to think about a person who “scrolled through” the entire tinder. like on the planet. everyone. everywhere. there’s nobody on your planet. wow. holy shit. that would be so cool.</p>

<p>end intermission.</p>

<hr />

<p>for now, i’ll leave this piece unfinished. there’s enough here already to have a discussion/debate around it!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[something???]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/img/blog/how%20to%20find%20internet%20friends.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/img/blog/how%20to%20find%20internet%20friends.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">a call for online democracy</title><link href="/blog/online-democracy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a call for online democracy" /><published>2022-09-21T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-21T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/online-democracy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/online-democracy"><![CDATA[<style>
* {
  font-family: "Times New Roman";
  font-size: 110%;
}
</style>

<p><strong>the urgent need for digital elections: today’s tech corporations are nothing but monarchies. now is the time to build online democracies.</strong></p>

<p>tech companies create places online for people to interact. they can be thought of as public squares — public places where people can come and talk, socialize, spend time together. but these public squares are, effectively, massive countries, and the company owning the country acts as the government. the “content policy” is effectively local laws, which can be different from country to country: the Tumblr country didn’t mind nudes (until recently), but at the Instagram country the nipple is a strict no-go. if something bad happens to you in one of these countries — say, a death threat in your DMs — you go to this country’s police department, that is, you hit “Report” button. in fact, you can freely choose whether to go to Instagram police department or to New York police department — that is, your offline state’s police. the choice is far from obvious. to many, these online countries are still a mystery.</p>

<p>the relationships between citizens and the state in offline countries are never simple, and they largely vary from place to place. but generally (ideally?), the idea is that the state maintains the essential infrastructure, and in exchange the citizens are paying a percent of their income. in a democracy, the citizens have a clear, transparent mechanism for expressing their views on how the government does its job: elections. various people (“politicians”) promise some changes to the existing policies and laws, and every citizen can cast their vote. i’m intentionally oversimplifying to avoid writing a 200-page thesis on what is a democracy.</p>

<p>surely, democracy is not perfect, but all the alternatives are much worse.</p>

<p>now, how are all major tech companies operating? what’s the relationship between their citizens (“users”) and their governments? to begin with, the relationship is entirely one-sided. the local laws (“terms of service”, “content policy”, etc.) are written by the platform owner, and citizens’ opinions are almost never taken into account. as a Twitter citizen who’s unhappy about some of Twitter’s rules and decisions, your situation is tragically binary: either you stay and accept your complete helplessness, or you delete your account.</p>

<p>citizens of these online states don’t pay taxes in the traditional understanding: technically, it’s all free, the tax is 0%. but — all citizens signed a contract, agreeing to two radically important things: (1) to watch ads — as many ads as the state decides to show them, (2) to have their every move tracked, recorded, and analyzed — for making profits. again, there is no option to opt out. you either stay and give up your freedom (but you get to stay where all your friends are), or you quit — and become a digital hermit.</p>

<p>it’s quite ironic that all Western tech giants were created in democratic states, yet of all possible options they chose monarchy: the CEO is the king, and what they say goes. of course, these digital states still have to comply with laws and regulations of the actual states they technically operate it, but they carry just about zero responsibility to the digital citizens who inhabit their digital lands. and while the unhappy citizens of offline states always had the option of going on the streets and protesting, here, in these digital lands, there’s nowhere to go. the best you can do is to #DeleteUber and then tweet about it. but it would hardly matter. a week later everyone will forget, and you’ll obediently reinstall the app.</p>

<p>of course, this “situation” was unavoidable, because none of the digital states were intended as such. they started as novel fun experiments, then they grew, matured, and turned into serious businesses, and as corporations they are primarily responsible to their shareholders, not to their “users”. it’s no surprise that they do everything they can to extract as much money as possible — while they still can. no matter what the spokespeople and ad spots tell you, the goal was never to “connect the world” or “make the world a better place”. the goal was always to make money. more money. more money.</p>

<p>so it would be naive at best to expect any social good from capitalism-rooted institutions. they are not going to change anything, unless there’s a threat of losing money — or an opportunity to make more money. the only way is to learn from their mistakes, and to create new, better online states — ones that embrace the core principles and ideas of democracy, and adapt them for digital lands.</p>

<p>here’s an outline of how such a New Tech Company could look and operate:</p>
<ol>
  <li>its major goal is to provide an online public space, not to create money</li>
  <li>every citizen has an equal right to the public space</li>
  <li>no surveillance, no tracking. period</li>
  <li>the citizens can contribute financially, if they choose to.</li>
  <li>the whole thing is subsidized by governments,</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>